<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Web | Builder's notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/categories/web/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-22T02:08:31-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://erick2red.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erick Pérez Castellanos]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Initial Commit]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/30/initial-commit/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-30T14:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/30/initial-commit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you can see, the migration to octopress started with the right foot. The blog
is up and running, and I just have to try three times. That was an easy one. The
first time I installed gentoo, took me about ten times to get it right.</p>

<p>I had some help, some guy named <em>zanshin</em> in <a href="irc://irc.freenode.net#octopress">#octopress at
freenode</a>, and the docs at
<a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress.org</a>. Now I've installed a new theme, added my
tweets stream, and I'm on the way to migrate my content from the previous
<a href="http://erick2red.wordpress.com">wordpress blog</a>. I have found a tool named
<a href="https://github.com/thomasf/exitwp">exitwp</a> in some post of another guy in the
same situation, and will test it soon.</p>

<p>You know what's missing ? You probably have see all those sites where you make
an account for yourself, and they ask you for an URL, like your site. Well,
I've been putting the wordpress site there. My bad, that should be set on a
central place, now I have to go changing that address everywhere. Maybe I should
make a redirect page in the wordpress blog, although I have to say, I've never
had too many readers.</p>

<p>Ohh, there's other stuff missing, one that I probably miss a lot. wordpress.com
have a spell checking utility, well, octopress hasn't one. It's up to my vim,
and I'm pretty lazy. Since english isn't my mother tongue. I'll have to look out
for error and typos.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging from Github with Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/28/blogging-from-github-with-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-28T19:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/28/blogging-from-github-with-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I've been looking finally at how to deploy an
<a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> based blog into <a href="http://github.com">Github</a>.
It's been a while since I saw octopress, and I always liked the motto,
it goes something like: blogging for hackers, and it sounds cool. I do have to
say I don't think of myself as a hacker, I'm more the guy who look to dig in
the code of every piece of software I use, even when I know I don't the time to.</p>

<p>Anyway, after a big while, and my request of my wordpress blog inclusion in
<a href="http://planet.gnome.org">Planet Gnome</a> went stalled. I decided to go using
Octopress, first I emailed the guys in Github since I have my doubts about
using their system for ranting about stuff not related with ruby/rails and
stuff. But they said they're fine with that. I do have to say I've been learning
some ruby these past days, there's this <a href="http://rubymonk.com">RubyMonk</a> site
which is pretty cool, and I found out
<a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=rubykoans">RubyKoans</a> too which are pretty
impressive too, although my lack of some supercharged environment is killing my
advance there. Well after all that I think is pretty logic to try this move.</p>

<h6>Here ends the drafting part</h6>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
