<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Builder's notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-23T12:15:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://erick2red.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erick Pérez Castellanos]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Calendar update]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/12/23/calendar-update/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-23T10:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/12/23/calendar-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This cycle I&#8217;ve been hard at work with <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Calendar">Calendar</a>. The idea is to get it in beta shape for GNOME 3.16 which is coming on march (or April, I never know, since it ends for developers before). I&#8217;ve being says these for two or three GNOME releases but this one is true. The bad about it, is that Contacts might get little love this time.</p>

<p>When I restarted work on Calendar this cycle it had been almost a year since my last commit. I got help this time. I have to thank every one involved in Calendar development, starting with <a href="http://www.hadess.net">Bastien Nocera</a>, and <a href="https://plus.google.com/+LapoCalamandrei">Lapo Calamandrei</a> whose design work has been amazing and last, but in anyway least, <a href="https://feaneron.wordpress.com/">Georges Basile Stavracas Neto</a>, who has offer us his coding skills and is the responsible for a bunch of new features in Calendar.</p>

<p>I would put here some mock-ups, and I know a more longer post is needed in order to let you know of some the stuff I&#8217;ve learned while developing the new features, but this going to be short one.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m about to make a 3.15.3 release of Calendar, even when I know is late, the release was last week. But I think is better to get it rolling, also there&#8217;s bunch of new features and I want people to be able to test it and comment on it.</p>

<p>Calendar new features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Initial search. This one is in very early stages, just search, and do nothing else.</li>
<li>Month-view reworked. We got a mock-up from Lapo with almost every issue the view had solved

<ul>
<li>Overflow of events on day cell is indicated and the events are shown on a popover</li>
<li>View has support for RTL locales</li>
<li>View has support for multiday events</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Edit/new dialog reworked. George got to work on this and fixed almost every issue the previous dialog had.

<ul>
<li>Moved the widget to use <code>GtkBuilder</code> UI files</li>
<li>Added new <strong>working</strong> time and date selectors</li>
<li>Added proper <code>GtkHeaderBar</code></li>
<li>Added calendar selector popover for when the dialog is used on event creation</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Calendar got the ability of hide/show calendars</li>
<li>Navigation buttons were relocated and <strong>jump to today</strong> was added</li>
<li>Calendar got a new 3d icon courtesy of <a href="http://jimmac.musichall.cz/">Jakub Steiner</a></li>
</ul>


<p>As you can see, Calendar has moved a lot forward. Hope you enjoy it.</p>

<p>To get you moving I posted <a href="https://twitter.com/erick2red/status/547087718904504320">these</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/erick2red/status/546360848147820547">screenshots</a> and little <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6kRKYLZYzl8">video</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GNOME 3.14]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/10/01/gnome-3-dot-14/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-01T10:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/10/01/gnome-3-dot-14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week GNOME 3.14 <a href="http://www.gnome.org/news/2014/09/gnome-3-14-released">was released</a>. I&#8217;ve been using my jhbuild copy since last Wednesday, and have to say I&#8217;m most happy with the improvements this cycle brought. I wanted to talk a bit about it, and this is one of the reason of this post.</p>

<p>As you can see in <a href="https://help.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/3.14/">the release notes</a> this version includes improvements around the whole stack: the network and sharing settings; the input system, with support for gestures and improved touchscreen support; the shell and a bunch of updated applications.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m most happy with the updates on GNOME Shell, this time the developers bring some pretty nifty animations to the Activities overview and windows. There&#8217;s also a whole set of changes for the developers using and targeting GNOME as platform. I&#8217;ll be talking a bit more on this latter.</p>

<h4>GNOME Shell</h4>

<p>I thought at first on describing you the animations added to latest iteration of the shell, but since an image is worth a thousands words. I guess a video will be worth 30 times per second the same, so <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cHtKkud6_is">here</a> it is this video showing you exactly that (Note: this is screencast was not made by me).</p>

<p>At first I thought I will be rapidly tired of those animations, usually, animations on the user interface looks good initially but over time just gets in the way of user daily activities. In this case it&#8217;s different, as in the case of those well thought features, I&#8217;ve been using the new shell for a over week a now, and I&#8217;m great surprised of how the animations don&#8217;t get in my way. Without being a magical thing, sometimes I realize of it when closing a window, or when opening one, but most of time I don&#8217;t even think of it. This speaks very highly on the craft of those designers and developers who accomplish so subtle change. Thanks.</p>

<h4>Developers improvements</h4>

<p>Now, this is the main reason of the post, even when I have left it to the end.</p>

<p>Life for the developers in GNOME has been improving steady over the last few cycles. GNOME hackers has come up with a DX hackfest, the interest in having a SDK for developing GNOME software has risen in the community, and projects like Christian&#8217;s <a href="https:///git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-builder">gnome-builder</a> are actively working towards this.</p>

<p>With GNOME 3.14, the awesome design team has come up with an updated version of <a href="https://developer.gnome.org/hig/stable/">GNOME Human Interface Guidelines</a>. I can&#8217;t stress enough the importance of this. Having a published and updated HIG provides uniformity and organization through the whole set of GNOME applications. I have it for around 4 days, and I have found myself going over to review a pattern, recheck a convention, etc. From simple things like margin, alignment and visual layout to others more detailed like how best use specific widgets available in Gtk+ and the contents of menus are explained there. The work done in getting those HIG ready is really impressive and we should be grateful as a platform of having this guidance for developers, either old ones and newcomers. I think is in order to thank great <a href="http://blogs.gnome.org/aday">Allan Day</a> and all the others for their work on this.</p>

<p>Finally, I want to mention Gtk+ improvements as a toolkit. First, the rewrite of Adwaita theme and its inclusion in Gtk+ will provide better experience for the user across different platforms and better looking in general. Second, and most important, the inclusion in Gtk+ of a new Gtk+ Inspector thanks to the work of <a href="http://blogs.gnome.org/mclasen">Matthias Clasen</a>. I won&#8217;t be talking much about Gtk+ Inspector since there have been already some post on it. I just wanted to mention it here because with the release of stable versions of Gtk+ and GNOME this is accessible to much more people than the selected team working on GNOME.</p>

<p>As before, I hope you enjoy GNOME 3.14 and its perks. See you around.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Contacts 3.14]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/09/22/contacts-3-dot-14/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T00:59:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/09/22/contacts-3-dot-14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s been almost seven months since my last post and much have happened. Across the next posts I&#8217;ll be telling you some of what&#8217;s been and what will come. Yet, today&#8217;s post i about <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Contacts">Contacts</a> and the improvements we made on this cycle and you will see when GNOME 3.14 gets released.</p>

<p>The biggest greatest work on these past months was implementing inline contact creation. For a long time I had Allan&#8217;s mockups lying around, there were, also, some bugs concerning the <em>&#8220;new contact dialog&#8221;</em> and its behavior. So we set the goal to fix those and implement the feature this cycle. Doing this I realize the some internals cleaning in Contacts is in order, but, since feeling it is a big task I decided to delay it and hack our current <a href="https://git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-contacts/tree/src/contacts-contact-editor.vala">ContactEditor</a> widget to make it able to work on the new flow.</p>

<p>Down, at the end, are some screenshots.</p>

<p>We also worked a bit on others details. There&#8217;s a list here:</p>

<ul>
<li>Updated all our dialogs to match latest Gtk+ design</li>
<li>Fixed the header-bar behavior and looks for selection and edit-mode</li>
<li>Fixed some bugs related to changing your default address bug. This included hacking into <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/Folks">folks</a> library, a work of which I am very proud.</li>
<li>Improved Adwaita dark variant support: Contacts maintained tweaked css code for colors definitions, we set out to use the defaults provided by the theme in order to work well with both variants.</li>
</ul>


<p>I hope you can enjoy latest version on Contacts when it&#8217;s released. Go, find and bugs and improvements and <a href="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=gnome-contacts">let us know</a></p>

<h4>A word on bugs</h4>

<p>I&#8217;ve been trying to maintain Contacts&#8217; bug list properly tagged and organized. In accomplishing that I&#8217;ve marked some as NEEDINFO, now, it&#8217;s been a while of this. I just wanted to let you know, I&#8217;ll be closing those bugs if they don&#8217;t get any updates before 3.14.1 is out on October 15.</p>

<p><a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/contacts_314/314-yay.png" rel="shadowbox" title="314-yay"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/contacts_314/thumbs/314-yay.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/contacts_314/header-bar-cleaned.png" rel="shadowbox" title="header-bar-cleaned"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/contacts_314/thumbs/header-bar-cleaned.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/contacts_314/inline-contact-creation.png" rel="shadowbox" title="inline-contact-creation"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/contacts_314/thumbs/inline-contact-creation.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Presenting GProxies]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/03/05/presenting-gproxies/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T00:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/03/05/presenting-gproxies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately, I&#8217;ve been working only from my laptop, and since I&#8217;m moving a lot usually
I find myself in situations where I need to change networks details to properly connect
to Internet. Now, <a href="https://www.gnome.org">GNOME</a> and <a href="http://www.gnome.org/projects/NetworkManager">NetworkManager</a> network configuration system
does a decent job at remembering your network settings across different network.</p>

<p>The thing about this, it&#8217;s that a network profile as defined in <strong>System Settings</strong> does not
keep your proxy configuration for that profile. So I took the task to wrote a small
tool for keeping different proxy configurations and allowing easy switching between them.</p>

<p>The tool is called <a href="https://github.com/erick2red/gproxies">GProxies</a>. It&#8217;s built using latest
<a href="http://www.gtk.org">Gtk+</a>, <strong>GLib</strong> and <strong>Vala</strong>. I tried to use the minimal amount of dependencies
so it won&#8217;t have that much noise.</p>

<p><strong>GProxies</strong> is designed with a very simple plugins system. Plugins are meant for
updating other applications&#8217; configuration whenever you select a different proxy setting
from the interface. For instance: I made a plugin for updating my git&#8217;s <code>http.proxy</code>
config automatically when selecting a different a proxy settings. There are two types
of plugins: one main <em>default plugin</em>, for setting GNOME system settings&#8217; proxy and
the others living inside <code>${XDG_DATA_DIR}/gproxies</code> designed to update other applications
configuration.</p>

<p>A plugin is defined by a folder named after the plugin in <code>${XDG_DATA_DIR}/gproxies</code>
with two or more files in it:</p>

<ul>
<li>a <code>plugin.ini</code> key-file. More details are explained <a href="https://github.com/erick2red/gproxies/blob/master/PLUGINS.md">here</a>.</li>
<li>an executable script/application which receives proxy details as calling arguments</li>
</ul>


<p>This way you can make plugins for changing the proxy in any applications
you want. I&#8217;ve made another <a href="https://github.com/erick2red/gproxies-plugins">repository</a> with the plugins I&#8217;ve write for myself.</p>

<p>Right now the tool is in a working state. I have some other improvements in mind,
such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>Add some interface to properly <em>enable/disable</em> plugins</li>
<li>Add the ability to install plugins from zipped files or remote sources</li>
<li>Add a direct-connection (no proxy enabled) state</li>
</ul>


<p>Finally, I&#8217;d like to say how much I enjoyed coding a small application for the GNOME
desktop. Gtk+ toolkit is perfect for this kind of task, with widgets which helps
enforcing GNOME HIG making an application fits properly in the desktop environment.
Also, Vala as a language it&#8217;s really powerful and composite widget templates from Gtk+
really speed up the development process. The code of <strong>GProxies</strong> is pretty simple,
and I guess it would make a nice reading for GNOME developer beginners.</p>

<p>Below, I present some screenshots. I hope someone will find this useful.</p>

<p><a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/gproxies_march_2014/gproxies_main.png" rel="shadowbox" title="gproxies_main"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/gproxies_march_2014/thumbs/gproxies_main.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/gproxies_march_2014/gproxies_showing_details.png" rel="shadowbox" title="gproxies_showing_details"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/gproxies_march_2014/thumbs/gproxies_showing_details.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Contacts 3.10]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/contacts-3-dot-10/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T12:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/contacts-3-dot-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is post was due for about two weeks ago. I&#8217;ve been very busy, so here it goes.</em></p>

<p>GNOME 3.10 was released almost three weeks ago. A huge number changes and improvements were made as you can see in
the <a href="https://help.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/3.10/">release notes</a>. Those changes affected <strong>Contacts</strong> as well.</p>

<p>This cycle the platform gained client-side decoration support from Gtk+ toolkit. We, in Contacts, also
incorporated a cool <a href="https://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/3.10/GtkHeaderBar.html">header bar</a>, which in our case has the perk of being splitted between the contacts list and
the main contact pane.</p>

<p>The change in Contacts I&#8217;m most proud of is the new Change AddressBook dialog. It&#8217;s an UI change that improved
the experience a lot and <a href="https://bugzilla.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=687220">clarified which is the active addressbook</a></p>

<p>Finally, under the hood, Contacts is starting to use most of the new widgets recently migrated into Gtk+ and
the template support landed this cycle.</p>

<p><strong>Edit</strong>: I owe you screenshots.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A week for releasing]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/07/16/a-week-for-releasing/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-16T08:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/07/16/a-week-for-releasing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve set a deadline for doing a weekly post. Well, last week, I missed. It was a really busy week.
I was building a web-page, and I haven&#8217;t done that in like 10 months or something so I had a lot to
catch up. It was fun, though. I&#8217;m right now looking forward to start playing around with <a href="http://weblog.rubyonrails.org/2013/6/25/Rails-4-0-final/">Rails 4</a></p>

<p>On the other side my Gnome duties caught up with me. I&#8217;ve been acting as Contacts maintainer with Alex for
a while now. But so far, he was doing the releasing part. I, usually, implemented new stuff, reviewed patches,
fixed bugs, but no more. This past week since Alex is on vacation I had to fill in doing the release.</p>

<p>I was prompted by Matthias Clasen for doing a release of gnome-contacts for the 3.9.4 development release of <a href="http://permalink.gmane.org/gmane.comp.gnome.devel.announce/339">Gnome</a>.
In the process, I realized I can&#8217;t log into master.gnome.org for the purposes of uploading the packages. So,
Mathias kindly offered himself to upload the package. Later I got my account authorized, and I was able to release
gnome-contacts-3.8.3. This latter one, I was surprised to see it packaged this morning into Archlinux.</p>

<p>These two releases are only bug fixes, yet there nasty bugs fixed there. You can read the <a href="https://git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-contacts/tree/NEWS">NEWS</a> file, or
the <a href="https://git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-contacts/log/">commit log</a> to find about.</p>

<p>What&#8217;s next on Contacts ? I want to implement New Contact flow inline and get rid of dialog, and close a
bunch of bugs around it. Also, yesterday I got a bug from Allan about updating a bit the selection pattern, and I
would like to work on it.</p>

<p><strong>Update</strong>: I have to thanks Jonh Wendell for his fix of the webcam bug.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[June update on Calendar]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/06/25/june-update-on-calendar/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-25T21:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/06/25/june-update-on-calendar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve made a commitment with myself of posting updates of the stuff I&#8217;m working
once a week. This one is the first, and I expected to be out by Monday, but an
<a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress">octopress</a> update and a plugin installation for handling image galleries
kept me from doing it.</p>

<p>By now, I&#8217;m a little tired of writing, therefore I&#8217;ll be quick about it.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago I restarted the work on <a href="https://live.gnome.org/Design/Apps/Calendar">Calendar</a> with the hope of adding a
bunch of new features in <strong>Gtk+</strong> to the project. I started by creating a
new branch, since I was sure the build would break a lot times in between, and
didn&#8217;t want to spoil <strong>master</strong></p>

<p>I&#8217;d set for myself a bunch of points I want to accomplish by rewriting the UI and
some of them has been done, some others, not yet. That&#8217;s the main reason why I keep
the branch still around. As soon as I feel the work is done, I&#8217;ll come back to work
on <strong>master</strong></p>

<p>I wanted to:</p>

<ol>
<li>Ditch <strong>clutter</strong> dependency. Use only Gtk+ widgets.</li>
<li>Include <a href="https://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/3.9/GtkSearchBar.html">GtkSearchBar</a>, <a href="https://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/3.9/GtkStack.html">GtkStack</a> and some of the latest Gnome UI guidelines</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/3.9/GtkBuilder.html">GtkBuilder</a>&#8217;s ui files as much as I can</li>
<li>Rework week-view to use <a href="https://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/3.9/GtkOverlay.html">GtkOverlay</a> instead of my own solution</li>
</ol>


<p>So far 1, 2 and 3 has been accomplished. Point number 4 is going well since I manage to
craft a day-view with the same requirements of week-view that does not need to
use <strong>GtkOverlay</strong>.</p>

<p>Some of the work done is showcased below</p>

<p><a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_june_2013/calendar-day-view.png" rel="shadowbox" title="calendar-day-view"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_june_2013/thumbs/calendar-day-view.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_june_2013/calendar-new-menu.png" rel="shadowbox" title="calendar-new-menu"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_june_2013/thumbs/calendar-new-menu.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_june_2013/calendar-search.png" rel="shadowbox" title="calendar-search"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_june_2013/thumbs/calendar-search.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_june_2013/calendar-updated.png" rel="shadowbox" title="calendar-updated"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_june_2013/thumbs/calendar-updated.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Software updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/11/30/software-updates/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-30T23:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/11/30/software-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s been a very long time since I posted anything.
You might not know, I live in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santiago_de_Cuba">Santiago de Cuba</a>, Cuba, one of the cities trashed by the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane_Sandy">hurricane
Sandy</a>. That left us a bunch of loses and lack of communication for weeks. We went
without power for at least 14 days, so you can imagine why I was not posting updates. Some time has
passed and the city is growing back from its ashes.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ve been working on <a href="https://live.gnome.org/Design/Apps/Calendar"><strong>Calendar</strong></a>, trying to get some minimal functioning
application, to get something out for you to use, and then I can continue
improving the rest. For now, I&#8217;ve focused on enable a fully working the &#8220;Event Details&#8221;
dialog. The thing is kinda clunky yet, but it works. It needs more polish
and heavy testing, though.</p>

<p>I also went and made a year-view implementation, which is almost fully
functional. This one was easy, was almost copy/paste from the old month-view
implementation.
The month-view also received a full face-lift. The previous version had some
super-rough edges when months didn&#8217;t fit in a 35 cells grid. That has been
fixed, our designers pulled some rabbits out of their hats. The new design,
which is already implemented suggest a scrolling
animation, but I want to be sure it works before going into it.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m trying to get <strong>Calendar</strong> in beta
shape for 3.8 release. I&#8217;m still need to implement three views: list-view,
day-view and week-view, and the search mechanism, with the results showing.
For the week-view I have an implementation which have scrolling issues,
I have to take care of.</p>

<p>Some minor mojo I don&#8217;t want to pass unnoticed:</p>

<ul>
<li>Squared buttons in the toolbar, thxs to Debarshy Ray for the suggestion and Cosimo&#8217;s libgd for the hack.</li>
<li>We added a proper use of <code>g_clear_object</code></li>
<li>Simple keyboard shortcuts, for <strong>Quit</strong> and change amount views.</li>
</ul>


<p>Now some screenshots</p>

<p><a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/edit-event-dialog.png" rel="shadowbox" title="edit-event-dialog"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/thumbs/edit-event-dialog.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/month-35-cell.png" rel="shadowbox" title="month-35-cell"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/thumbs/month-35-cell.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/month-42-cell.png" rel="shadowbox" title="month-42-cell"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/thumbs/month-42-cell.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/year-view-first.png" rel="shadowbox" title="year-view-first"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/thumbs/year-view-first.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/year-view-second.png" rel="shadowbox" title="year-view-second"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_dec_2012/thumbs/year-view-second.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A challenge of locales]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/10/09/a-challenge-of-locales/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-09T09:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/10/09/a-challenge-of-locales</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When developing an application aiming for everyone worldwide to use, there are certain challenges
you will face. Right now, mine is fighting laziness and locales.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m developing some widget for specifying a date and I&#8217;ve been struggling with date formats across locales
So, after reading a huge number of manpages, source-code, and so on I stumble on this code.</p>

<pre><code>#include &lt;langinfo.h&gt;
#include &lt;locale.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
  setlocale(LC_ALL,"");
  printf("%s\n",nl_langinfo(D_FMT));
  exit(EXIT_SUCCESS);
}
</code></pre>

<p>This will show me your date format according to your locale.
What I will ask, compile and run this code in your pc, and post the answer here along with your locales.</p>

<p>See you around.</p>

<p><em>Update</em>: Thxs for the comments. Two things: I&#8217;ve just updated the code, thxs to Tom, adding <strong>setlocale</strong> line made the code works. Second: Thxs to Tommi (first comment). That was the info I was looking for.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making you own widget]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/08/21/making-you-own-widget/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-21T13:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/08/21/making-you-own-widget</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago, I was in <a href="irc://irc.gnome.org/gtk+">gtk+ irc channel</a> and there was someone making the
kind of question I&#8217;ve done myself like a hundred times. Thankfully the guys
in the channel hasn&#8217;t got tired of me, yet. They are pretty helpful once they
realize you&#8217;ve done your homework.</p>

<p>Once you start hacking around with Gtk+, the next thing you&#8217;ll want to do
is to make your own widgets. And for that there&#8217;s little to none documentation,
guides or tutorial. There&#8217;s a huge amount of knowledge in Gtk+ source itself, but most
people doesn&#8217;t like to read code, or doesn&#8217;t know how to. They should, <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2012/04/learn-to-read-the-source-luke.html" title="Read the Source, Luke">though</a></p>

<p>Here I&#8217;ll try to show, from the newbie point, how Gtk+ draw things,
and what&#8217;s the guidelines to accomplish certain tasks when making
widgets for Gtk+. This is, as well, a reminder for myself, since most times I
need to go into IRC to ask the same things all over again.</p>

<p>I will split the post in three main sections which corresponds to the important
parts in a widget lifetime.</p>

<h4>Size handling</h4>

<p>One of the thing you need when you&#8217;re making widgets is knowing the
dimensions everything will have inside. Size requisition and allocation is the
step where this happens.</p>

<p>Explanations of this process appears here in <a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/stable/GtkWidget.html#GtkWidget.description">GtkWidget&#8217;s documentation</a>.
It includes most of the size requisition process and geometry management.</p>

<p>Gtk+ widgets are arranged in a hierarchy where container widgets pack others
and handle its size and allocation. The widget containing yours will ask the
natural and minimal size you want to have, and after making some internal
calculations will assign your widget a size and allocation. The first
part is called <em>size requisition</em> and the second <em>size allocation</em>. The
virtual methods you need to implement here are:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>For size requisition</em></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/stable/GtkWidget.html#gtk-widget-get-preferred-width"><code>gtk_widget_get_preferred_width</code></a></li>
<li><a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/stable/GtkWidget.html#gtk-widget-get-preferred-width-for-height"><code>gtk_widget_get_preferred_width_for_height</code></a></li>
<li><a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/stable/GtkWidget.html#gtk-widget-get-preferred-height"><code>gtk_widget_get_preferred_height</code></a></li>
<li><a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/stable/GtkWidget.html#gtk-widget-size-allocate"><code>gtk_widget_get_preferred_height_for_width</code></a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><em>For size allocation</em>:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/stable/GtkWidget.html#gtk-widget-size-allocate"><code>gtk_widget_size_allocate</code></a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, what to do on each one of these methods ?, Calculate what size you want for
the widget, and return it. Let&#8217;s say you have a widget which have a text saying
<strong>&#8220;Hello&#8221;</strong> inside, then, you need to ask <a href="http://developer.gnome.org/platform-overview/stable/pango">Pango</a> to calculate the width and
height for you, add the margins and padding (if you want to take those into
account) and return the size accordingly.</p>

<p>What&#8217;s width-for-height and height-for-width methods for ?, Widget have by
definition one request-mode, its width depends on its height or the other way
around. This is totally decided by you, accordingly to the type of widget you&#8217;re
creating. The purpose of these methods is to retrieve these measures, the width
of a widget given a specified height, and viceversa. About this part,
read carefully the docs above and go asking in the IRC for more help if stuck.</p>

<p>One thing to keep in mind is that the allocated size to your widget, could be
not the same you requested in the <code>get_preferred</code> methods, so the widget should
work with the given allocation instead of any other measure.</p>

<p><em>Rule of thumb</em>: Implement the four methods of size requisition almost always,
and the size-allocate one if needed.</p>

<h4>Drawing stuff</h4>

<p>This is the core of the matter, but there&#8217;s no much to tell in here. Use
<a href="http://developer.gnome.org/platform-overview/stable/cairo">cairo</a> to draw, the API is pretty simple. Use cairo primitives to draw
inside the implementation of <code>draw</code> virtual method. There, is given a context
which is clipped from one of the <code>GdkWindow</code> of the widget, you should draw
in that context. Other than this, here are some remarks:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>How to draw an icon from the theme into the <code>cairo_context_t</code> ?. Obtain a
<code>GdkPixbuf</code> from the icon with <a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gtk/stable/GtkIconTheme.html#gtk-icon-theme-load-icon"><code>gtk_icon_theme_load_icon</code></a> or
<a href="http://developer.ginome.org/gtk/stable/GtkIconTheme.html#gtk-icon-info-load-symbolic"><code>gtk_icon_info_load_symbolic</code></a> depending on the icon, and draw it to the
context with <a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gdk/stable/gdk-Cairo-Interaction.html#gdk-cairo-set-source-pixbuf"><code>gdk_cairo_set_source_pixbuf</code></a></p></li>
<li><p>How do I get my lines subpixel thin ?. Turns out that cairo can draw lines
thinner than one pixel, but for that to happen you need to place the cairo
starting point in the middle of the pixel, so the drawing can be made, and look
just like you want.</p>

<pre><code>/* a vertical 0.3 pixel line */
cairo_set_line_width (cr, 0.3);
cairo_move_to (cr, 10, 10.4);
cairo_rel_line_to (cr, 0, 10);
cairo_stroke (cr);
</code></pre></li>
</ul>


<p>Finally, use whenever you need <a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/stable/GtkStyleContext.html#gtk-render-background"><code>gtk_render_background</code></a>,
<a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/stable/GtkStyleContext.html#gtk-render-frame"><code>gtk_render_frame</code></a> family and friends over any alternative drawing you
could think of doing. These functions will get colors and border size
and radius from the CSS theming engine, therefore you&#8217;re spared a bunch of work.</p>

<h4>Processing events</h4>

<p>How to receive and handle mouse, touch and button events. My first attempt
to catching and handling event was to implement virtual method <code>button_press</code>
and <code>button_release</code>, that didn&#8217;t worked. Not that easily.</p>

<p>For catching input events in your custom widget, you will need a <code>GdkWindow</code>
suited for those purposes. The preferred idiom here is:</p>

<ul>
<li>In your <code>realize</code> method, create a <code>GdkWindow</code> with <a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gdk/stable/gdk-Windows.html#gdk-window-new"><code>gdk_window_new</code></a> and
set its type to <code>GDK_WINDOW_CHILD</code>, this would assure to catch the input events if
they occur inside you window. After created the window, call
<a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gdk/stable/gdk-Windows.html#gdk-window-show"><code>gdk_window_show</code></a> to show it. You will use
<a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gdk/stable/gdk-Windows.html#gdk-window-set-user-data"><code>gdk_window_set_user_data</code></a> to relate the window with your widget.</li>
<li>In your <code>size_allocate</code> method, you need to place the window where it should,
by using <a href="http://developer.gnome.org/gdk/stable/gdk-Windows.html#gdk-window-move-resize"><code>gdk_window_move_resize</code></a>.</li>
<li>Now, you can implement <code>button_press</code> and the likes of them to handle your
events.</li>
</ul>


<p>There are virtual methods for handling mouse button presses, and a releases,
but no for high-level actions as click and double-click, you need to detect those
by detecting sequences of presses and releases. Nonetheless, for double-click the
<code>GdkEventButton</code> will have the type field set to <code>GDK_2BUTTON_PRESS</code> which will
certainly help. For key-press/release events, I have to say, I haven&#8217;t
had nothing to do with those yet. So, that will be left to the next time.</p>

<h4>Putting things together</h4>

<p>I won&#8217;t paste the code entirely, I&#8217;ll just describe the order in which the above
mentioned steps will most likely occur.</p>

<p>Usually, as you must have guessed by now, the first thing your widget will
receive is a request for its preferred size using
<code>gtk_widget_get_preferred_width</code> and friends. After that, the
parent will follow to allocate the size, there your implementation of
<code>size_allocate</code> will run, and then, the painting will happen.
About the <code>realize</code> part, it will happens almost anytime,
the only thing you can be sure of is: it will happens before your widget had to
paint itself. One thing worth mentioning is that a widget could be allocated a
bunch of times before it ever gets to the painting part.</p>

<p>About a full example of code, one the simplest widgets for showing all
of this is <code>GtkButton</code>. You can read the source of in the Gtk+ tree. Here&#8217;s
the header: <a href="http://git.gnome.org/browse/gtk+/tree/gtk/gtkbutton.h"><code>gtkbutton.h</code></a> and the source <a href="http://git.gnome.org/browse/gtk+/tree/gtk/gtkbutton.c"><code>gtkbutton.c</code></a>. As I said
above, reaching into Gtk+ internals is the best way to learn to use the toolkit
and the framework.</p>

<h4>Conclusion</h4>

<p>Obviously this a pretty simple post about some of the
more common tasks you&#8217;ll meet with when making a custom widget. There are
several more complex widgets which are far from this, but those are left for
later.</p>

<p>Hope it helps, and if you find any mistake, please contact me immediately so I can
fix it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving to Fedora]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/08/21/moving-to-fedora/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-21T12:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/08/21/moving-to-fedora</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been using <a href="http://www.archlinux.org/">Archlinux</a> for about 4 years now, and I&#8217;ve been pretty happy
about it. The thing is, as I become more involved in Gnome development, I&#8217;ve feel
the best distro for such a purpose is <a href="http://fedoraproject.org/">Fedora</a>.</p>

<p>Now,  you can argue a bunch of
powerful reasons, but the people who package Gnome in Fedora knows
Gnome internals, so the chance you&#8217;ll end up getting a better experience is
higher. I should tell Gnome packagers in Archlinux to stay a little bit
closer to upstream Gnome developers. Another reason for staying with Arch would
have been to test Gnome across different distros, and I know that would help,
but I felt I needed a change.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s another point, since I&#8217;m dedicating more time now to develop stuff, I
spent less time configuring stuff and tweaking my system, I&#8217;m starting to see my
laptop as a tool for development, not the toy it used to be. The only thing I
require of a distro right now is:</p>

<ul>
<li>Having a package of vim. I&#8217;ll install the plugins myself.</li>
<li>Having gcc/g++ and the man pages of those. Which I found yesterday I don&#8217;t
have in Fedora.</li>
<li>Having devhelp, and GLib/Gtk+ docs.</li>
<li>Ohh, and not having <strong>KDE</strong> installed by default.</li>
</ul>


<p>So, by now, I&#8217;ve been on Fedora for almost a month according to <em>last</em>, and I&#8217;m
pretty happy with it.</p>

<p>See you soon, to let u know some Calendar advances.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updates to gnome-calendar]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/07/03/updates-to-gnome-calendar/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-03T16:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/07/03/updates-to-gnome-calendar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s been long time since I published any stuff, errr. I&#8217;ve
been busy. So, to the point.</p>

<p>Calendar is moving forward, slower than I would like, but is moving. From the
last time, I&#8217;ve started the implementation of the event-view, and I say started
cause there&#8217;s missing functionality yet, but the widgets part is almost done.
For now, it deletes your events, so be careful, that&#8217;s the only button that
really works. I&#8217;ve set in-place some code to enable notifications, but that will
have to wait a little yet. The toolbar has got some changes,
mostly added behavior to the change between views, and some internal
refactoring.</p>

<p>The most important stuff is: the screenshots you&#8217;ll see below will
show you one thing, the event-view need some redesign to occupy all that empty
space. There&#8217;s host/guest part still missing implementation, but I know it won&#8217;t
fill all the space. On the other hand, I&#8217;ll need some symbolic icon for the
reminders, to show in the views (monthly, daily, etc.). There&#8217;s still the issue
of the navigation controls presentation, which I don&#8217;t like been shown by
pressing <Ctrl>, but that will come eventually.</p>

<p>This work is pretty skeleton-like, there&#8217;s a bunch of stuff that needs to be
retouched, so, any thing you find, feel free to reach me.</p>

<p>Now the shots:
The first one is the month-view, the only one working right now, and the others
are of the event-view.</p>

<p><a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_aug_2012/edit-event.png" rel="shadowbox" title="edit-event"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_aug_2012/thumbs/edit-event.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_aug_2012/month-view-showing-sources.png" rel="shadowbox" title="month-view-showing-sources"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_aug_2012/thumbs/month-view-showing-sources.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_aug_2012/view-event.png" rel="shadowbox" title="view-event"><img src="http://erick2red.github.com/images/galleries/calendar_aug_2012/thumbs/view-event.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Calendar]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/06/01/introducing-calendar/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-01T09:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/06/01/introducing-calendar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This should be old news for some, but good news for community I hope. About a
week I uploaded the firsts bits of Gnome Calendar application as sketched
<a href="https://live.gnome.org/Design/Apps/Calendar">here</a>. It just do very few stuff, but it&#8217;s a start. The main design is done,
and I&#8217;ll keep working on it.</p>

<p>The code was uploaded to github at first, but after talking with gnome&#8217;s servers
sysadmins we agree the code could be hosted in <a href="http://git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-calendar">git.gnome.org</a>.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m very happy of getting the project live, I know there&#8217;s a lot of work ahead,
and I&#8217;ll be on it alternating with Gnome Contacts&#8217; work, which is mostly done by
Alex.</p>

<p>I have to thanks all the gnome hackers for its great response.</p>

<p>Keep in touch.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm on Planet Gnome]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/05/16/im-on-planet-gnome/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-16T22:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/05/16/im-on-planet-gnome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since last Friday I&#8217;m a proud member of <a href="http://planet.gnome.org">Planet Gnome</a>.
I notice my last two post on Planet Gnome feed, and was a huge joy. After the
initial excitement I realize what a great responsibility encloses the fact of
being able of publish there, and certain fear went deep into my bones.</p>

<p>Anyway, and introduction is mandatory. My name is: Erick Pérez Castellanos, and
I&#8217;m a software developer from Cuba. I studied Computer Science like 4 years ago
or so, and I&#8217;ve been using Linux since for ever it seems. I became involved with
Gnome last year, after wanting to for a very long time. I&#8217;ve been contributing
to Contacts, as you can see here in the archive of the blog, and I&#8217;m planning to
keep on. So, till next time, I&#8217;ll see you around.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finished migration]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/05/03/finished-migration/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-03T10:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/05/03/finished-migration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can say the migration is finished. There&#8217;s till my blog online <a href="http://wordpress.com">Wordpress.com</a>
but that could be left for later. I think on putting a redirect there, or just
taking it down.</p>

<p>The thing is that octopress is a pretty comfortable scheme. It allows me to
write and sanitize my blog at home, or wherever I have my laptop, no matter if
I&#8217;m online or not. The point is I can do a bunch of stuff in my pc without
internet connection, which is a very rare affair in under-developed countries.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s still stuff missing, and I&#8217;ll try to add it on the way. I would like update my twitter
stream with my posts automatically from <strong>rake deploy</strong> task, but since Twitter
now uses OAuth, that became a mess, and I don&#8217;t understand OAuth scheme yet, so
I&#8217;ll have to let it be for a while. I was concern at first for my spelling, but
now anymore, my vim has spell checking, and after change <strong>rake new_post</strong> task
to launch vim with spell checking set on, it&#8217;s way better than Wordpress
correction system.</p>

<p>So, as you can see, so far so good, I like this pretty much, and think is easier
and better than Wordpress. I encourage you people to join.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Initial Commit]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/30/initial-commit/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-30T14:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/30/initial-commit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you can see, the migration to octopress started with the right foot. The blog
is up and running, and I just have to try three times. That was an easy one. The
first time I installed gentoo, took me about ten times to get it right.</p>

<p>I had some help, some guy named <em>zanshin</em> in <a href="irc://irc.freenode.net#octopress">#octopress at
freenode</a>, and the docs at
<a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress.org</a>. Now I&#8217;ve installed a new theme, added my
tweets stream, and I&#8217;m on the way to migrate my content from the previous
<a href="http://erick2red.wordpress.com">wordpress blog</a>. I have found a tool named
<a href="https://github.com/thomasf/exitwp">exitwp</a> in some post of another guy in the
same situation, and will test it soon.</p>

<p>You know what&#8217;s missing ? You probably have see all those sites where you make
an account for yourself, and they ask you for an URL, like your site. Well,
I&#8217;ve been putting the wordpress site there. My bad, that should be set on a
central place, now I have to go changing that address everywhere. Maybe I should
make a redirect page in the wordpress blog, although I have to say, I&#8217;ve never
had too many readers.</p>

<p>Ohh, there&#8217;s other stuff missing, one that I probably miss a lot. wordpress.com
have a spell checking utility, well, octopress hasn&#8217;t one. It&#8217;s up to my vim,
and I&#8217;m pretty lazy. Since english isn&#8217;t my mother tongue. I&#8217;ll have to look out
for error and typos.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting warnings out of Clutter]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/28/getting-warnings-out-of-clutter/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-28T23:59:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/28/getting-warnings-out-of-clutter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s been a while since I blogged anything. Well, I actually did some ranting
about starting this new blog. But that really doesn&#8217;t count. I should make a
post saying what I&#8217;ve been up to. But I&#8217;m lazy. I&#8217;ve been:</p>

<ul>
<li>Learning some Qt (and I doesn&#8217;t like it, maybe I tell something about this
later)</li>
<li>Using <a href="https://github.com/fritzy/SleekXMPP">SleekXMPP</a> python library</li>
<li>Learning ruby (Did I said this already ?)</li>
<li>Learning <a href="http://www.clutter-project.org">Clutter</a>, and here we stop.</li>
</ul>


<p>While I was trying to pull some code using Clutter and Gtk+, before you ask, I
was trying to put GtkWidget inside Clutter Actors to get some fancy animation, I
got into some minor troubles, which I think those newbies like me out there
should know.</p>

<p>First, if you read the blog of the might Emmanuele Bassi (Clutter&#8217;s author and
main developer) you then came across this post
<a href="http://blogs.gnome.org/ebassi/2012/03/17/had-a-dream/">Had a dream</a>. I did, and I wanted to get
those warning they talk about so my code would need to be modified pretty much
anything when those API get deprecated. Well, I didn&#8217;t, I mean I used
deprecated API and my compiler wasn&#8217;t throwing me warnings. Someone told me
that I needed to use a decent set of compilers flags, and I tried, nah, still
nothing. I went into IRC, I found help there and after a while, I was told to
add this to my compiler options</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>-DCLUTTER_VERSION_MIN_REQUIRED=CLUTTER_VERSION_1_10</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This finally solved the issue and I&#8217;m having pretty warnings  every time I use
an old method which should be destroyed in a couple of months.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging from Github with Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/28/blogging-from-github-with-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-28T19:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/04/28/blogging-from-github-with-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&#8217;ve been looking finally at how to deploy an
<a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> based blog into <a href="http://github.com">Github</a>.
It&#8217;s been a while since I saw octopress, and I always liked the motto,
it goes something like: blogging for hackers, and it sounds cool. I do have to
say I don&#8217;t think of myself as a hacker, I&#8217;m more the guy who look to dig in
the code of every piece of software I use, even when I know I don&#8217;t the time to.</p>

<p>Anyway, after a big while, and my request of my wordpress blog inclusion in
<a href="http://planet.gnome.org">Planet Gnome</a> went stalled. I decided to go using
Octopress, first I emailed the guys in Github since I have my doubts about
using their system for ranting about stuff not related with ruby/rails and
stuff. But they said they&#8217;re fine with that. I do have to say I&#8217;ve been learning
some ruby these past days, there&#8217;s this <a href="http://rubymonk.com">RubyMonk</a> site
which is pretty cool, and I found out
<a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=rubykoans">RubyKoans</a> too which are pretty
impressive too, although my lack of some supercharged environment is killing my
advance there. Well after all that I think is pretty logic to try this move.</p>

<h6>Here ends the drafting part</h6>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gnome Foundation Membership Accepted]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/03/06/gnome-foundation-membership-accepted/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-06T15:41:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/03/06/gnome-foundation-membership-accepted</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m the proud owner of a Gnome Foundation membership. That sounded awfull, anyway. It&#8217;s true , today the Gnome Fundation Comitee approved my application, and I set up my mail alias.</p>

<p>This is a great news to me, and I think it would be to anyone. There&#8217;s point you can&#8217;t miss though, this means more responsibilty doing a good job to make <a href="http://www.gnome.org">Gnome Project</a> great.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gnome Account Application]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/03/02/gnome-account-application/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-02T11:49:36-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/03/02/gnome-account-application</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, while I was talking with the Gnome Contacts developer came up the issue of me having an account. I wasn&#8217;t familiar with the process, he point me to the <a href="https://live.gnome.org/NewAccounts">page in question</a>, and I filled the application for the account. The process took a day, this morning while I was solving another bug in Gnome Contact the mails reached my inbox telling me about the new account being setup in an hour or so. I finished the work in the patch. Went right to the instruction for using Git as the Gnome standards requires and <a href="http://git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-contacts/commit/?id=3eae3e0501539c1d3de7c062abaaa591f79ba1d9">pushed the patch</a> by my own. Now I have a few commits already in <a href="http://git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-contacts">git.gnome.org/gnome-contacts</a> but this one is the first one I make myself.</p>

<p>Now I&#8217;m still waiting for the Gnome Foundation decision on my application to be a member yet, this is huge joy. I&#8217;m looking forward to contribue more to Gnome, it&#8217;s an amazing world with amazing people and great programmers, and I&#8217;m pretty happy to be prt of it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
