<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gnome | Builder's notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/categories/gnome/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-23T12:15:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://erick2red.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erick Pérez Castellanos]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Calendar update]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/12/23/calendar-update/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-23T10:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/12/23/calendar-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This cycle I've been hard at work with <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Calendar">Calendar</a>. The idea is to get it in beta shape for GNOME 3.16 which is coming on march (or April, I never know, since it ends for developers before). I've being says these for two or three GNOME releases but this one is true. The bad about it, is that Contacts might get little love this time.</p>

<p>When I restarted work on Calendar this cycle it had been almost a year since my last commit. I got help this time. I have to thank every one involved in Calendar development, starting with <a href="http://www.hadess.net">Bastien Nocera</a>, and <a href="https://plus.google.com/+LapoCalamandrei">Lapo Calamandrei</a> whose design work has been amazing and last, but in anyway least, <a href="https://feaneron.wordpress.com/">Georges Basile Stavracas Neto</a>, who has offer us his coding skills and is the responsible for a bunch of new features in Calendar.</p>

<p>I would put here some mock-ups, and I know a more longer post is needed in order to let you know of some the stuff I've learned while developing the new features, but this going to be short one.</p>

<p>I'm about to make a 3.15.3 release of Calendar, even when I know is late, the release was last week. But I think is better to get it rolling, also there's bunch of new features and I want people to be able to test it and comment on it.</p>

<p>Calendar new features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Initial search. This one is in very early stages, just search, and do nothing else.</li>
<li>Month-view reworked. We got a mock-up from Lapo with almost every issue the view had solved

<ul>
<li>Overflow of events on day cell is indicated and the events are shown on a popover</li>
<li>View has support for RTL locales</li>
<li>View has support for multiday events</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Edit/new dialog reworked. George got to work on this and fixed almost every issue the previous dialog had.

<ul>
<li>Moved the widget to use <code>GtkBuilder</code> UI files</li>
<li>Added new <strong>working</strong> time and date selectors</li>
<li>Added proper <code>GtkHeaderBar</code></li>
<li>Added calendar selector popover for when the dialog is used on event creation</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Calendar got the ability of hide/show calendars</li>
<li>Navigation buttons were relocated and <strong>jump to today</strong> was added</li>
<li>Calendar got a new 3d icon courtesy of <a href="http://jimmac.musichall.cz/">Jakub Steiner</a></li>
</ul>


<p>As you can see, Calendar has moved a lot forward. Hope you enjoy it.</p>

<p>To get you moving I posted <a href="https://twitter.com/erick2red/status/547087718904504320">these</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/erick2red/status/546360848147820547">screenshots</a> and little <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6kRKYLZYzl8">video</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GNOME 3.14]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/10/01/gnome-3-dot-14/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-01T10:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/10/01/gnome-3-dot-14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week GNOME 3.14 <a href="http://www.gnome.org/news/2014/09/gnome-3-14-released">was released</a>. I've been using my jhbuild copy since last Wednesday, and have to say I'm most happy with the improvements this cycle brought. I wanted to talk a bit about it, and this is one of the reason of this post.</p>

<p>As you can see in <a href="https://help.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/3.14/">the release notes</a> this version includes improvements around the whole stack: the network and sharing settings; the input system, with support for gestures and improved touchscreen support; the shell and a bunch of updated applications.</p>

<p>I'm most happy with the updates on GNOME Shell, this time the developers bring some pretty nifty animations to the Activities overview and windows. There's also a whole set of changes for the developers using and targeting GNOME as platform. I'll be talking a bit more on this latter.</p>

<h4>GNOME Shell</h4>

<p>I thought at first on describing you the animations added to latest iteration of the shell, but since an image is worth a thousands words. I guess a video will be worth 30 times per second the same, so <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cHtKkud6_is">here</a> it is this video showing you exactly that (Note: this is screencast was not made by me).</p>

<p>At first I thought I will be rapidly tired of those animations, usually, animations on the user interface looks good initially but over time just gets in the way of user daily activities. In this case it's different, as in the case of those well thought features, I've been using the new shell for a over week a now, and I'm great surprised of how the animations don't get in my way. Without being a magical thing, sometimes I realize of it when closing a window, or when opening one, but most of time I don't even think of it. This speaks very highly on the craft of those designers and developers who accomplish so subtle change. Thanks.</p>

<h4>Developers improvements</h4>

<p>Now, this is the main reason of the post, even when I have left it to the end.</p>

<p>Life for the developers in GNOME has been improving steady over the last few cycles. GNOME hackers has come up with a DX hackfest, the interest in having a SDK for developing GNOME software has risen in the community, and projects like Christian's <a href="https:///git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-builder">gnome-builder</a> are actively working towards this.</p>

<p>With GNOME 3.14, the awesome design team has come up with an updated version of <a href="https://developer.gnome.org/hig/stable/">GNOME Human Interface Guidelines</a>. I can't stress enough the importance of this. Having a published and updated HIG provides uniformity and organization through the whole set of GNOME applications. I have it for around 4 days, and I have found myself going over to review a pattern, recheck a convention, etc. From simple things like margin, alignment and visual layout to others more detailed like how best use specific widgets available in Gtk+ and the contents of menus are explained there. The work done in getting those HIG ready is really impressive and we should be grateful as a platform of having this guidance for developers, either old ones and newcomers. I think is in order to thank great <a href="http://blogs.gnome.org/aday">Allan Day</a> and all the others for their work on this.</p>

<p>Finally, I want to mention Gtk+ improvements as a toolkit. First, the rewrite of Adwaita theme and its inclusion in Gtk+ will provide better experience for the user across different platforms and better looking in general. Second, and most important, the inclusion in Gtk+ of a new Gtk+ Inspector thanks to the work of <a href="http://blogs.gnome.org/mclasen">Matthias Clasen</a>. I won't be talking much about Gtk+ Inspector since there have been already some post on it. I just wanted to mention it here because with the release of stable versions of Gtk+ and GNOME this is accessible to much more people than the selected team working on GNOME.</p>

<p>As before, I hope you enjoy GNOME 3.14 and its perks. See you around.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Contacts 3.14]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/09/22/contacts-3-dot-14/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T00:59:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/09/22/contacts-3-dot-14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been almost seven months since my last post and much have happened. Across the next posts I'll be telling you some of what's been and what will come. Yet, today's post i about <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Contacts">Contacts</a> and the improvements we made on this cycle and you will see when GNOME 3.14 gets released.</p>

<p>The biggest greatest work on these past months was implementing inline contact creation. For a long time I had Allan's mockups lying around, there were, also, some bugs concerning the <em>"new contact dialog"</em> and its behavior. So we set the goal to fix those and implement the feature this cycle. Doing this I realize the some internals cleaning in Contacts is in order, but, since feeling it is a big task I decided to delay it and hack our current <a href="https://git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-contacts/tree/src/contacts-contact-editor.vala">ContactEditor</a> widget to make it able to work on the new flow.</p>

<p>Down, at the end, are some screenshots.</p>

<p>We also worked a bit on others details. There's a list here:</p>

<ul>
<li>Updated all our dialogs to match latest Gtk+ design</li>
<li>Fixed the header-bar behavior and looks for selection and edit-mode</li>
<li>Fixed some bugs related to changing your default address bug. This included hacking into <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/Folks">folks</a> library, a work of which I am very proud.</li>
<li>Improved Adwaita dark variant support: Contacts maintained tweaked css code for colors definitions, we set out to use the defaults provided by the theme in order to work well with both variants.</li>
</ul>


<p>I hope you can enjoy latest version on Contacts when it's released. Go, find and bugs and improvements and <a href="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=gnome-contacts">let us know</a></p>

<h4>A word on bugs</h4>

<p>I've been trying to maintain Contacts' bug list properly tagged and organized. In accomplishing that I've marked some as NEEDINFO, now, it's been a while of this. I just wanted to let you know, I'll be closing those bugs if they don't get any updates before 3.14.1 is out on October 15.</p>

<p><a class="fancybox" href="/images/galleries/contacts_314/314-yay.png" rel="shadowbox" title="314-yay"><img src="/images/galleries/contacts_314/thumbs/314-yay.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="/images/galleries/contacts_314/header-bar-cleaned.png" rel="shadowbox" title="header-bar-cleaned"><img src="/images/galleries/contacts_314/thumbs/header-bar-cleaned.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="/images/galleries/contacts_314/inline-contact-creation.png" rel="shadowbox" title="inline-contact-creation"><img src="/images/galleries/contacts_314/thumbs/inline-contact-creation.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Contacts 3.10]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/contacts-3-dot-10/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T12:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/contacts-3-dot-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is post was due for about two weeks ago. I've been very busy, so here it goes.</em></p>

<p>GNOME 3.10 was released almost three weeks ago. A huge number changes and improvements were made as you can see in
the <a href="https://help.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/3.10/">release notes</a>. Those changes affected <strong>Contacts</strong> as well.</p>

<p>This cycle the platform gained client-side decoration support from Gtk+ toolkit. We, in Contacts, also
incorporated a cool <a href="https://developer.gnome.org/gtk3/3.10/GtkHeaderBar.html">header bar</a>, which in our case has the perk of being splitted between the contacts list and
the main contact pane.</p>

<p>The change in Contacts I'm most proud of is the new Change AddressBook dialog. It's an UI change that improved
the experience a lot and <a href="https://bugzilla.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=687220">clarified which is the active addressbook</a></p>

<p>Finally, under the hood, Contacts is starting to use most of the new widgets recently migrated into Gtk+ and
the template support landed this cycle.</p>

<p><strong>Edit</strong>: I owe you screenshots.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A week for releasing]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/07/16/a-week-for-releasing/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-16T08:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2013/07/16/a-week-for-releasing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've set a deadline for doing a weekly post. Well, last week, I missed. It was a really busy week.
I was building a web-page, and I haven't done that in like 10 months or something so I had a lot to
catch up. It was fun, though. I'm right now looking forward to start playing around with <a href="http://weblog.rubyonrails.org/2013/6/25/Rails-4-0-final/">Rails 4</a></p>

<p>On the other side my Gnome duties caught up with me. I've been acting as Contacts maintainer with Alex for
a while now. But so far, he was doing the releasing part. I, usually, implemented new stuff, reviewed patches,
fixed bugs, but no more. This past week since Alex is on vacation I had to fill in doing the release.</p>

<p>I was prompted by Matthias Clasen for doing a release of gnome-contacts for the 3.9.4 development release of <a href="http://permalink.gmane.org/gmane.comp.gnome.devel.announce/339">Gnome</a>.
In the process, I realized I can't log into master.gnome.org for the purposes of uploading the packages. So,
Mathias kindly offered himself to upload the package. Later I got my account authorized, and I was able to release
gnome-contacts-3.8.3. This latter one, I was surprised to see it packaged this morning into Archlinux.</p>

<p>These two releases are only bug fixes, yet there nasty bugs fixed there. You can read the <a href="https://git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-contacts/tree/NEWS">NEWS</a> file, or
the <a href="https://git.gnome.org/browse/gnome-contacts/log/">commit log</a> to find about.</p>

<p>What's next on Contacts ? I want to implement New Contact flow inline and get rid of dialog, and close a
bunch of bugs around it. Also, yesterday I got a bug from Allan about updating a bit the selection pattern, and I
would like to work on it.</p>

<p><strong>Update</strong>: I have to thanks Jonh Wendell for his fix of the webcam bug.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
