<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Linux | Builder's notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/categories/linux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-22T09:29:08-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://erick2red.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erick Pérez Castellanos]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Presenting GProxies]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/03/05/presenting-gproxies/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T00:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2014/03/05/presenting-gproxies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately, I've been working only from my laptop, and since I'm moving a lot usually
I find myself in situations where I need to change networks details to properly connect
to Internet. Now, <a href="https://www.gnome.org">GNOME</a> and <a href="http://www.gnome.org/projects/NetworkManager">NetworkManager</a> network configuration system
does a decent job at remembering your network settings across different network.</p>

<p>The thing about this, it's that a network profile as defined in <strong>System Settings</strong> does not
keep your proxy configuration for that profile. So I took the task to wrote a small
tool for keeping different proxy configurations and allowing easy switching between them.</p>

<p>The tool is called <a href="https://github.com/erick2red/gproxies">GProxies</a>. It's built using latest
<a href="http://www.gtk.org">Gtk+</a>, <strong>GLib</strong> and <strong>Vala</strong>. I tried to use the minimal amount of dependencies
so it won't have that much noise.</p>

<p><strong>GProxies</strong> is designed with a very simple plugins system. Plugins are meant for
updating other applications' configuration whenever you select a different proxy setting
from the interface. For instance: I made a plugin for updating my git's <code>http.proxy</code>
config automatically when selecting a different a proxy settings. There are two types
of plugins: one main <em>default plugin</em>, for setting GNOME system settings' proxy and
the others living inside <code>${XDG_DATA_DIR}/gproxies</code> designed to update other applications
configuration.</p>

<p>A plugin is defined by a folder named after the plugin in <code>${XDG_DATA_DIR}/gproxies</code>
with two or more files in it:</p>

<ul>
<li>a <code>plugin.ini</code> key-file. More details are explained <a href="https://github.com/erick2red/gproxies/blob/master/PLUGINS.md">here</a>.</li>
<li>an executable script/application which receives proxy details as calling arguments</li>
</ul>


<p>This way you can make plugins for changing the proxy in any applications
you want. I've made another <a href="https://github.com/erick2red/gproxies-plugins">repository</a> with the plugins I've write for myself.</p>

<p>Right now the tool is in a working state. I have some other improvements in mind,
such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>Add some interface to properly <em>enable/disable</em> plugins</li>
<li>Add the ability to install plugins from zipped files or remote sources</li>
<li>Add a direct-connection (no proxy enabled) state</li>
</ul>


<p>Finally, I'd like to say how much I enjoyed coding a small application for the GNOME
desktop. Gtk+ toolkit is perfect for this kind of task, with widgets which helps
enforcing GNOME HIG making an application fits properly in the desktop environment.
Also, Vala as a language it's really powerful and composite widget templates from Gtk+
really speed up the development process. The code of <strong>GProxies</strong> is pretty simple,
and I guess it would make a nice reading for GNOME developer beginners.</p>

<p>Below, I present some screenshots. I hope someone will find this useful.</p>

<p><a class="fancybox" href="/images/galleries/gproxies_march_2014/gproxies_main.png" rel="shadowbox" title="gproxies_main"><img src="/images/galleries/gproxies_march_2014/thumbs/gproxies_main.png" /></a>
<a class="fancybox" href="/images/galleries/gproxies_march_2014/gproxies_showing_details.png" rel="shadowbox" title="gproxies_showing_details"><img src="/images/galleries/gproxies_march_2014/thumbs/gproxies_showing_details.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A challenge of locales]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/10/09/a-challenge-of-locales/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-09T09:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/10/09/a-challenge-of-locales</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When developing an application aiming for everyone worldwide to use, there are certain challenges
you will face. Right now, mine is fighting laziness and locales.</p>

<p>I'm developing some widget for specifying a date and I've been struggling with date formats across locales
So, after reading a huge number of manpages, source-code, and so on I stumble on this code.</p>

<pre><code>#include &lt;langinfo.h&gt;
#include &lt;locale.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
  setlocale(LC_ALL,"");
  printf("%s\n",nl_langinfo(D_FMT));
  exit(EXIT_SUCCESS);
}
</code></pre>

<p>This will show me your date format according to your locale.
What I will ask, compile and run this code in your pc, and post the answer here along with your locales.</p>

<p>See you around.</p>

<p><em>Update</em>: Thxs for the comments. Two things: I've just updated the code, thxs to Tom, adding <strong>setlocale</strong> line made the code works. Second: Thxs to Tommi (first comment). That was the info I was looking for.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving to Fedora]]></title>
    <link href="http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/08/21/moving-to-fedora/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-21T12:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erick2red.github.com/blog/2012/08/21/moving-to-fedora</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been using <a href="http://www.archlinux.org/">Archlinux</a> for about 4 years now, and I've been pretty happy
about it. The thing is, as I become more involved in Gnome development, I've feel
the best distro for such a purpose is <a href="http://fedoraproject.org/">Fedora</a>.</p>

<p>Now,  you can argue a bunch of
powerful reasons, but the people who package Gnome in Fedora knows
Gnome internals, so the chance you'll end up getting a better experience is
higher. I should tell Gnome packagers in Archlinux to stay a little bit
closer to upstream Gnome developers. Another reason for staying with Arch would
have been to test Gnome across different distros, and I know that would help,
but I felt I needed a change.</p>

<p>There's another point, since I'm dedicating more time now to develop stuff, I
spent less time configuring stuff and tweaking my system, I'm starting to see my
laptop as a tool for development, not the toy it used to be. The only thing I
require of a distro right now is:</p>

<ul>
<li>Having a package of vim. I'll install the plugins myself.</li>
<li>Having gcc/g++ and the man pages of those. Which I found yesterday I don't
have in Fedora.</li>
<li>Having devhelp, and GLib/Gtk+ docs.</li>
<li>Ohh, and not having <strong>KDE</strong> installed by default.</li>
</ul>


<p>So, by now, I've been on Fedora for almost a month according to <em>last</em>, and I'm
pretty happy with it.</p>

<p>See you soon, to let u know some Calendar advances.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
